A Guide to the Burwell Family Papers, 1736-1786
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Burwell Family Papers, 1736-1786, 1736-1810.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 64.4
15 items.
Burwell family.; Carter Burwell, 1716-1756.; Nathaniel Burwell, 1750-1814.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1964.
Alternative Form
All but the printed materials are available on microfilm M-1557, and M-1558. Some items are available in transcription TR/06 and TR/59.
Biographical/Historical Information
Carter Burwell of James City County studied at the College of William and Mary in 1734. He married Lucy Ludwell Grymes.
Nathaniel Burwell, born in 1750, was the son of Carter and Lucy Burwell. He inherited Carter's Grove but moved to Clark County in the Shenandoah Valley where he built and lived in Carter Hall. He married Susanna Grymes in 1772. She bore him eight children before her death in 1788. After Susanna's death, Burwell married Lucy Page Baylor who also bore him eight children. He died in 1814.
Scope and Content Information
Account books kept by Carter Burwell (1716-1756) and his son, Nathaniel Burwell (1750-1814), for their plantation, Carter's Grove, James City County, Va. One account book contains accounts of their neighbor, James Bray (d. 1744), who ran a tannery and shoemaking shop at his plantation; others contain accounts for the building of Carter's Grove. Also, a Book of Common Prayer and a Bible owned by Carter Burwell and four stud horse advertisements and an equine poster concerning the pedigree and performance of the "late Eclipse."
Accounts include the names of James Anderson, Gov. Norborne Berkeley, Baron de Botetourt, John Bracken, Mrs. Ann Burwell, Armistead Burwell, John Carter, George Charleton, Josiah Chowning, Mrs. Davenport, Dr. John Minson Galt, William Gooch, Philip Grymes, Matthew Hubbard, William Moody, Hugh Nelson, John Norton, Dr. William Pasteur, Dr. John de Sequeyra, Richard Taliaferro, William Trebell, Robert Waller, Henry Wetherburn, Thomas Wharton, Ralph Wormeley, and many others.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Burwell family.
Persons:
Anderson, James, ca. 1740-1809.; Botetourt, Norborne Berkeley, Baron de, ca. 1718-1770.; Bracken, John, d. 1818.; Burwell, Ann.; Burwell, Armistead.; Burwell, Carter, 1716- 1756.; Burwell, Nathaniel, 1750-1814.; Carter, John.; Charleton, George.; Chowning, Josiah, d. 1772.; Davenport, Mrs.; De Sequeyra, John, 1712-1795.; Galt, John M., 1744-1808.; Gooch, William, Sir, 1681- 1751.; Grymes, Philip.; Hubbard, Matthew; Moody, William.; Nelson, Hugh.; Norton, John 1719-1777.; Pasteur, William, d. 1791.; Taliaferro, Richard, d. ca. 1789.; Trebell, William, d. 1789.; Waller, Robert.; Wetherburn, Henry, d. 1760.; Wharton, Thomas, ca. 1712-ca. 1748.; Wormeley, Ralph, 1715- 1790.
Subjects:
Architecture, Colonial--Virginia--James City County.; Horse shows--Virginia.; Horses--Breeding.; Plantations--Virginia--James City County.; Shoemakers--Virginia.; Tanning--Virginia.
Genre and Form Terms:
Ledgers (account books)--Virginia--James City County--19th century.; Obituaries-- Virginia--19th century.
Geographical Names:
Carter's Grove (Va.)
Contents List
- "The Pedigree, performance, and produce, of the famous running horse, Eclipse," 1791., 1 printed page. (Oversize 1X)
  Brief biography of Eclipse, a famous race horse once owned by William, Duke of Cumberland. Printed by J. Jones, Chapel-Street, Soho.
- "Telemachus," 29 Mar 1810., 1 printed page. (Folder 1)
  Stud advertisement for Telemachus a horse owned by Beverly Whiting and kept at Bullskin, four miles from Charles-Town.
- "The Celebrated English stallion, Buzzard," Mar 1805. (Folder 1)
  Stud advertisement for the race horse Buzzard, owned by Nathaniel Rives on the Nottoway River in Greensville County. Advertisement was printed by Dickson and Pescud, Printers, Petersburg.
- "An account of Mr. Carter Burwell's Apparel, etc., etc.," [1756] (Folder 2)
  List of Mr. Burwell's clothes contained in two trunks, with valuation.
- Obituary of Mrs. Lucy Burwell, [1843], 1 page. (Folder 2)
  Written by Mr. John Hay.
- Newspaper clippings, 1843-1873 and n.d., 5 newspaper clippings mounted on one sheet. (Oversize 1X)
  Includes two wedding announcements and three obituaries. The wedding announcements are for Rosalie Lisle Wheat and John Townsend Burwell. The obituaries are for George H. Burwell, Francis B. Whiting and Nathaniel Burwell.
- "Carter's Grove sold." (Folder 2)
  Newspaper clipping concerning the sale of Carter's Grove by Dr. E. G. Booth to Mr. T. C. Bislord.
- Envelope: "Obituaries of Col. Nathaniel Burwell of Carter Hall and Lucy Burwell, his wife. (Folder 2)
- Envelope: "Grand mother's obituary lent me by cousins Mary Blair and Lucy Whiting. Belle Mayo. (Folder 2)
- "The famous high blooded English horse Hambleton," 1807., 1 printed page. (Oversize 2X)
  Stud advertisement for Hambleton. Printed by W. G. Lyford in Staunton.
- "The noted and much admired English horse Knowsley," 1807., 1 printed page. (Oversize 2X)
  Stud advertisement for Knowsley. Printed by Samuel Pleasants, Jr. in Richmond.
- Obituary of Francis B. Whiting, 1867., Newspaper clipping. (Folder 3)
  Removed from Book of common prayer.
- Births., Printed form with manuscript insertions. (Folder 3)
  List of Whiting family births. Includes information for Francis B. Whiting, his wife Mary Burwell Whiting, and Francis b. Whiting, Jr. Removed from the Book of common prayer.
- Note, 1886., 2 pages. (Folder 3)
  Note by Robert Carter Randolph concerning the provenance of the Book of Common Prayer. Removed from the Book of common prayer.
- Ledger, 1736-1746. (Oversize 1X)
- Ledger, 1738-1753. (Oversize 1X)
- Ledger, 1764-1776. (Oversize 1X)